[SPEAKER_01]: So, people who are familiar with the hillside hermitage teachings will likely have heard the word context used with reference to the practice.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, can we go over what exactly that context is, and is it something one finds already there, or is it something one needs to cultivate?
[SPEAKER_00]: So, eh...
[SPEAKER_00]: The context is definitely not something that you fabricate.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not an idea.
[SPEAKER_01]: That it's kind of like...
[SPEAKER_00]: I mean, there is a component of, let's say, intellectual reflection to it, but it would be more accurate to see it at the level of an emotional perspective, or an emotional attitude, rather than just an idea that you can kind of keep at the back of your mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, in the most practical sense, you could say,
[SPEAKER_00]: The context refers to your present state of mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the context that underlies your actions and that even if you ignore it, it's still there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Which is an important thing to understand.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's not that you're doing the context necessarily consciously, but you're certainly responsible for cultivating the context by acting out of states of, let's say, greed or aversion that might be there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Even if you're not saying to yourself, I shall act out of this context and cultivate this context, through your actions coming out of that state of mind,
[SPEAKER_00]: That is the context that you are increasing and strengthening.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's why the suttas would say that somebody who... they would describe it as giving attention to the sign of gratification or the theme of gratification.
[SPEAKER_00]: That when somebody does that, their sensual desire increases.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's not necessarily that you
[SPEAKER_00]: Tell yourself, I shall come to cultivate the context of sensuality being pleasant and agreeable.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's... your mind has that context already of finding pleasure in these things and then by you acting out of it, you make it worse.
[SPEAKER_00]: You make it even more easy for your mind to focus on the pleasant aspect of sensuality and overlook the danger.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, there is a right context and a wrong context.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, then, in a way, it's useful to recognize that this is not a new... that the development of the context is not a new thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's something that you've already been doing all the time.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's just, more often than not, the wrong kind of context.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, the context of, like I said, finding pleasure in sensuality,
[SPEAKER_00]: Resisting the unpleasant, that's another context, that's pretty much by default there.
[SPEAKER_00]: And then, if you don't question it and you just go about your day as an ordinary person, you will be cultivating that context.
[SPEAKER_01]: And distraction is to cultivate the context of ignorance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly, yeah.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, that's another one that's that's pretty... you don't need to make any effort.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's going to be there by itself, just because that's the starting point of an ignorant mind.
[SPEAKER_00]: So then, if you don't make an effort to... that's why it's so important to question the motivation behind your actions, which doesn't, as we've often clarified, is not about like a reason that you can kind of explain at arm's length.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's at that emotional level,
[SPEAKER_00]: Which means you need to ask yourself, like you need to uncover the motivation that's already there.
[SPEAKER_00]: Not like you choose the motivation.
[SPEAKER_00]: Rather, if you look, you will see there is some kind of force that's driving you to do X or Y.
[SPEAKER_00]: And that's where you would be able to see, oh, is there a context of wanting to, like you said, distraction, or wanting to turn away from the neutral feeling of not much going on.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, that's a context that would be there, enduring on its own.
[SPEAKER_00]: And by overlooking it, you're acting out of it, and you're making it even more
[SPEAKER_00]: You're taking yourself even farther away from the wholesome context of non-distraction.
[SPEAKER_01]: Or from recognizing any context whatsoever.
[SPEAKER_00]: Exactly.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, because that's the other problem with the context of the unwholesome ones, like the context of greed, aversion and delusion, of sensuality, ill-will, cruelty.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's that they... you can't mindfully
[SPEAKER_00]: Cultivate that context.
[SPEAKER_00]: In other words, you can't mind... mind... mindfully engage in sensuality, mindfully engage in ill-will, mindfully engage in cruelty, mindfully engage in distraction.
[SPEAKER_00]: That's a contradiction in terms.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you would... you would then realize that, well, that's pretty much the primary harm of these things.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, even if I don't... even if I don't see an immediate harm from it yet,
[SPEAKER_00]: The simple fact that it obstructs your self-awareness means like it's it's pretty much like taking an intoxicant.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like you don't know what you're going to end up doing if you take enough of an intoxicating substance.
[SPEAKER_00]: Well, it's the same thing.
[SPEAKER_00]: These contact... and actually the Buddha called it like intoxication.
[SPEAKER_00]: And one of the translations for this term, that's often rendered as heatfulness, is non-intoxication, apamādha, which is exactly what you will be cultivating.
[SPEAKER_00]: Like, you would realize your normal context, your normal state of being, is one of intoxication with one thing or the other.
[SPEAKER_00]: It doesn't necessarily have to be full-on core sensual pleasure.
[SPEAKER_00]: You're just intoxicated with
[SPEAKER_00]: In the broadest sense, with life as such, with your ambitions, your goals, the things that you value, your health, protecting your health for its own sake, not even for the sake of practice, but just because you resist illness as such, intoxication with youth, as if, you know, it were ultimately in your control,
[SPEAKER_01]: Yeah, or like, I can do it because I'm still young, and even if it goes wrong, I have time in the future to correct my mistakes.
[SPEAKER_01]: It's all based on assumptions that are dangerous.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, and also the... even if you don't have, like, something that fits neatly,
[SPEAKER_00]: In one of those three categories, well, ultimately, you will be intoxicated with some sight, sound, smell, taste, touch, or even mental image.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, you might have even ideas about the practice, and they might be right ideas, but you often see that like how
[SPEAKER_00]: Somebody could become so engaged on that level of mental figuring out and intellectualizing that that becomes pretty much their way of scratching the itch, their way of cultivating the same context of unwholesome kind of seeking gratification at the wrong place.
[SPEAKER_00]: It would be fed through that same... Because that is the context that you're already following, that's already driving you to act in such ways, well, the more you act in such ways, the more you will be strengthening the context.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's like...
[SPEAKER_00]: Like a bully, the more you allow him to tell you what to do and harass you, and you don't push back against it, the more he will be doing it.
[SPEAKER_01]: Now, earlier you said that you cannot mindfully engage in sensuality.
[SPEAKER_01]: That that's a contradiction, that acting out of sensuality, by definition, means that you've lost the perspective.
[SPEAKER_01]: Does that mean that the pleasure of sensual pleasures is a memory?
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you indulge, which means that you've basically lost the perspective, and at some point you sort of come out of it, and then you say, wrongly, that is what's pleasant.
[SPEAKER_01]: So, in a sense, the pleasure is a sort of a recollection.
[SPEAKER_01]: Like, you're not actually
[SPEAKER_00]: Right.
[SPEAKER_00]: Yeah, well, if you were...
[SPEAKER_00]: It's always with reference to either the past or the future.
[SPEAKER_00]: Because you can't really be enjoying...
[SPEAKER_00]: When you look at the central state of mind, it's never about what you're getting now.
[SPEAKER_00]: It's about the next pump of pleasure that would come.
[SPEAKER_00]: So, it's... in a way, yeah, it's always either a memory or something that you anticipate.
Oh, yeah, that's it.